Guide to the Albert V. Baez Papers SC1052
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Albert V. Baez papers
1949-1995
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baez, Albert V.
SC1052
13.75 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The materials consist of research files, correspondence, teaching materials, biographical material, publications, photographs, and some experimental equipment.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research.
Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of research files, correspondence, teaching materials, biographical material, publications, photographs, and some experimental equipment.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Vinicio Baez, Ph.D. (1912-2007) was a prominent Mexican-American physicist, and the father of singers Joan Baez and Mimi Fariña.
Dr. Baez earned his bachelor's degree in mathematics from Drew University in 1933 and his master's degree in physics from Syracuse University in 1935. In 1936, he married Joan Chandos Bridge, the daughter of an Episcopalian minister. The couple became Quakers and had three daughters, Pauline, Joan and Mimi. Together they moved to California, where he pursued a doctorate in physics.
In 1948, along with Stanford University professor Paul Kirkpatrick (1894–1992), Baez developed the X-ray reflection microscope for examination of living cells. This microscope is still used today in medicine. Baez received his PhD in physics from Stanford in 1950. After graduating, he developed zone plates—concentric circles of alternating opaque and transparent materials to use diffraction instead of refraction to focus X-rays. Unfortunately, much of his work had to await the development of synchrotron X-rays sources several decades later.
As the Cold War arose in the 1950s, Dr. Baez's talents were in high demand for the developing arms race. However, influenced by his family's pacifist beliefs, he refused lucrative war industry jobs, preferring instead to devote his career to education and humanitarianism. From 1950 to 1956, he held a professorship at the University of Redlands, where he continued his X-ray research. Dr. Baez took a yearlong leave to work with UNESCO in 1951, stationing his family in Baghdad to establish the physics department and laboratory at Baghdad University. In 1959, Dr. Baez accepted a faculty position at MIT, and moved his family to the Boston area. In 1960, working with the Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory in Cambridge, MA, he developed optics for an X-ray telescope. Later that year he moved to the faculty of Harvey Mudd College, and moved his family to Claremont, California. From 1961 to 1967, he directed science teaching for UNESCO in Paris.
Dr. Baez was the author of the textbook The New College Physics: A Spiral Approach (1967). He was also the co-author of the textbook The Environment and Science and Technology Education (1987) and the memoir A Year in Baghdad (1988). Dr. Baez made almost 100 films about physics for the Encyclopædia Britannica Educational Corp from 1967 to 1974. He also chaired the Commission on Education of the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources from 1979 to 1983.
After his retirement, Dr. Baez occasionally delivered physics lectures and was president of Vivamos Mejor/USA, an organization founded in 1988 to help impoverished villages in Mexico. Its projects include preschool education, environmental projects, and community and educational activities. In 1991, the International Society for Optical Engineering awarded him and Kirkpatrick the Dennis Gabor Award for pioneering contributions to the development of X-ray imaging microscopes and X-ray imaging telescopes. In 1995, the Hispanic Engineer National Achievement Awards Corporation (HENAAC) established the Albert V. Baez Award for Technical Excellence and Service to Humanity. Dr. Baez himself was inducted into the HENAAC Hall of Fame in 1998.
He died of natural causes March 20, 2007 at age 94.
Stanford University -- Faculty.; X-ray microscopy; Physics -- Experiments.; Physics.; X-ray holography; Baez, Albert V.
- Papers
  - X-Ray Telescope (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Professor Paul Kirkpatrick (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - X-Ray Optics Paper (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - X-Ray Pictures (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Soft X-Ray Microscopes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - X-Ray holography (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Richard B. Hoover Papers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Renaissance of X-Ray Optics (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - X-Ray Pictures using Zone Plates at Lawrence Livermore National Lab (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Baez's Ph.D. Thesis (Copy) – Stanford University, 1949 Aug (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Introduction to Optics using Microwaves ( Draft by Baez, Reprint of a Review Article on Microwave Spectroscopy) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Optics Education (Reprints, booklets, Journal Issues, on teaching of Optics) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Technology in Education (Printed Articles) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Technology in Education (Booklets) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stanford University Physics 23 Course (Baez’s Syllabus and Lectures) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stanford University Physics 29 Course (Baez's Syllabus and Lectures) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Stanford University Physics 21 Course (Baez’s Syllabus and Lectures) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Harvard Summer School (Photographs of Students, 5 sections), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Preparation of Harvard Summer School Lectures (Description of Auto Lectures) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Harvard Summer School, Micro-Notes I (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Harvard Summer School, Micro-Notes II (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harvard Summer School, Overhead Transparencies (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Auto Lecture Transcripts I (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Auto Lecture Transcripts II (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Auto Lecture Transcripts III (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Harvard Summer School Pre Tests (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Auto Lecture Illustrations (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Harvard Summer School, Students (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Harvard Summer School, Improvement Printed, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence with Harvard Professor Purcell (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Science Teaching at UNESCO, Research and Outline (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Copies of popular articles of the B.F. Skinner vs. Noam Chomsky debate(s) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Central Washington Speech, X-Ray Optics plus Transparencies (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Talk at Sonoma State University, Physics Department, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Holography Publication with G. Castro Reprints, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pre-prints of 3 papers by A.V. Baez (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - A.V. Baez, Biographical Sketches and Press Clippings (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A.V. Baez, Diary and Science Notes, Summer 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings from newspapers and magazines (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Professor Manfred von Ardenne of Dresden, 1956-57 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - X-Rays, Various reprints, 1966-68 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - X-Ray Research, Various reprints, some manufacturers literature (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - X-Ray Pictures II, Various unlabeled X-ray photos(probably taken by Baez at the University of Redlands), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bibliography, various published bibliographies on X-Ray Radiography (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - X-Ray Astronomy, Various reprints and some correspondence (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - X-Ray Sources, reprints of solar and interstellar x-rays (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - X-Ray Spectrographic Chart, X-Ray lines of the elements (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - X-Ray Detectors, reprint on scintillators, report on outer space detection (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - X-Ray Mic. Lit., Correspondence and reprints on X-Ray Microscopy (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - X-Ray Microscopy New Tool, Notes, Lectures, Correspondence on X-Ray Microscopy, 1953-64 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The X-Ray Microscope AVB, A review manuscript on the X-ray Microscope by A.V. Baez (probably unpublished), 1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - X-Ray Mic. Reprints, various reprints about the x-Ray Microscopy (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - X-Ray Microscopy a Report, presented by A.V. Baez at the Cancer Conference, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Patent Disclosure, Patent request for an X-Ray Telescope, Report on the Erosion of plastic at Cornell, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - ONR Report, by A.V.Baez, X-Ray Focusing by Diffraction, Annual Summary Report, 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Orbiting X-Ray Telescopes, Smithsonian Notes and Papers (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Baez X-Ray from Paul Kirpatrick, Correspondence and Notes, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Holography Interferometry, Reprints and Pre-print (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Holography Advanced, Reprints and one Report (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Holography Advanced II, Reprints and one Pre-print (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - S.P.I.E., Correspondence and Literature (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Schawlow, Reprints (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Optics Holography-Soroko/USSR, Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Optics, Stroke, Reprints and Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Optics Valasek, Notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Optics/Wolf, Correspondence and Reprints (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Optics Holography, Neural, Reprints (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Optics Woodruff, Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Holography Acoustic, Reprints and Journal Issue (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Holography, Misc. Correspondence and Reprint (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Optics- Kastler, Correspondence and Reprints (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Optics Kock, Correspondence and Reprints (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Optics -Leith, Reprints and Pre-prints (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Optics-Microwaves, Reprints and Lab Experiment Instructions (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Optics –Mikulka Electrical Analog, Reprints (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Optics- MW Holography, Reprints (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Optics- Index Reprint, An index of the reprints in the area of Optics (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - A- Quantum (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - B- Space (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - C-Image (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - D-Microscope (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - E-Film (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - F-Spectroscopy (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - G-Interferometry (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - H-History (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - I-Laser (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - J-Resolution (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - K-Binocular (3-D) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - L-Physics of (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - M- Lenses (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - N-Ete (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - O-X-Rays (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - UV (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - P-Reflection (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Q-Institutions (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - R-Glass (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - S-fourier and Correlation (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - T- Coherence (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - U-bibliography (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - V-Information Theory (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - W-Color (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - X-detectors (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Y-Polarized Light (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Z-zone Plates (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Zone plate (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Descriptive Geometry with 3-D Figures by Imre Pal (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Overheads for Holography Seminar (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Baez Video for viewing with Diffraction Grating", 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 5)
  - Redlands hologram and reconstruction, 35mm slide (of gratings?) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - lenses, loupe and magnifying glasses (Box 5)
  - Kiss-II, Mini KISS, Mini Train: Clear plastic sheets carefully wrapped in 3 tubes (Box 5)
  - Fresnel lenses and holograms (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Filters, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Micro Mini Multiple Holograms (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Polaroid (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Difraction Gradings" (sic) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Apertures (Circular, Tip Split, Single Slit) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Multiplex Co. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Glass hologram (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - YIP hologram (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mounted optical gratings (Box 6)
  - "Eastman Spectroscopic Plates"--zone plates and slides on x-ray telescope. (Box 6)
    General note
    these are lantern slides only, the only real gold zone plate is the one in Box 5 in its own mailing package
  - X-ray Conf, 33055 (Box 6)
  - X-ray zone plate (Box 6)
  - Optics – Gabor (Box 6)
  - Gabor (correspondence) (Box 6)
  - Rogers, Gordon Film, Information (Box 6)
  - Physics/Manual (Box 6)
  - Mounted gratings (contains many smaller envelopes) (Box 6)
  - e-mail correspondence with Sean Johnston (Scotland) on early holography expts. (Box 6)
  - "X-ray hand", 1 film reel(s) (16mm) (Box 6)
  - Lantern slide zone plate (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Dr. George Castro and joint papers; referee correspondence (Box 6)
  - A Guide to Holograph (draft) (Box 6)
  - Fisher; Konhious (?)--two wrapped lantern slides, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - loose papers (Box 6)
  - X-ray optical Images (Copies #11, #38 & #41) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - A Study of Diffraction of Microscopy by Donald D. Robinson (Vols 1 & 2) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - EBF Misc Lasers Holography and Plans (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Holography: ideas for a course and a book plus experiments (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Holography Introductory (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Holography Jeong (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Holography Introduction (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Reference Materials (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Holography Proposal: Baez (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Holography: Firms, Resources, People (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Holography: Correspondence – A. Baez (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Films and Other Audio-Visual Aids (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Baez: Manual Holography (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Holography: Information Sheet Requests (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Holography Information Sheets Originals (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Zone Plates Holography X Rays (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Zone Plates (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Zone Plate Misc. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Zone Plate Gust (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Zone Plate Paul (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Bottema/Zone Plates (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Optics/El-Sum (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Greguss (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Optics/Jannossy (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Zone Plate – Reprint List (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Optics – Mollenstedt (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Holography – Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Rogers, G.L (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Gabor, Notes (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Annual Meeting of the Advanced Light Source Users Association, 1993 Oct 21-22 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Proceedings: Advanced Optical Manufacturing and Testing (San Diego), 1990 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Some loose papers, reports & correspondence (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Pioneering Photos, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Large envelope: Lit. search S-Ray zone plate holography (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - X-Ray Optics – Magnus (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - X-Ray Conference (on X-Ray Astronomy at Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory, Cambridge, Mass.), 1960 Sep 20 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Theses, Marc Montel, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - SPIE (Preconference), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - SPIE, July 21-26, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - X-Ray misc SPIE, 1995 Jul 12 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - X-ray Research (Including April 1984 Physics Today issue with Underwood and Attwood article) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - X-rays (includes Early Reflections), 34892 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Holography Lecture O.U. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Holography Book and Auto lectures (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Buckbee Mears Co. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Henke + X-ray optics (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Holography Lecture (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Research Winick Synchrotron – Wigglers (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Davis, Robt Celescope, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - G. L. Rogers, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Holography Speech (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - X-Rays (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Janos Kirz/A.V. Baez, X-Ray (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - SPIE Paper 1546-38 (Ross borrowed), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Check list of facilities and Equipt. (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Holography Auto Lect. + Lecture (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - AAAS Holography (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - R-Hoover - X-rays, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Tyndall Lecture – Final Outline (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - X-Rays (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - X-Ray Astronomy Reprints (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ultra-Violet Reprints (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Astrophysical Project Description (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Note for Holographic Activities at Lawrence Hall of Science (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Holographic Manual from Metrologic Instruments (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Color Diffraction – Notes and Lectures (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Diffraction Microscopy – Notes (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Diffraction Microscopy – Reprints (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - University of Redlands Research – Notes and Letters (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - American Cancer Society – Report of Research Accomplished (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Copy of Letter to Nahum Joel, miscellaneous reprints on x-ray imaging (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ted (Edward) Fisher – student of Baez at the University of Redlands, Letters and Notebook (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Thesis (Honors Project) of Edward Fisher (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Research Reports of Baez's students (3) at the University of Redlands (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Overhead foils for the talk on Holography, Technical requirements for Holography Demonstrations, Manufacturing Literature for Holography Photography (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Special Issue Magazine with 3-D Photographs (with special eyeglasses) (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Drafts and scripts for a slide and tape presentation on Holography (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Reprints on Holography (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Optics Experiments for Physics students at Harvard, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2016-132
  - "I", 1974-06 (Box 1, Folder 1)